<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exhortation to the byshops to deale brotherly with theyr brethren</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1572</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111888</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847148</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12168</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00280)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12168)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 222:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exhortation to the byshops to deale brotherly with theyr brethren</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Stroud?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Hemel Hemstead? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1572]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Suggested place of publication and printer, and publication date, from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes an appeal to the bishops to answer "An admonition to the parliament" (STC 10847). Register is continuous. The appeal begins with a caption title on B1 recto that reads: An exhortation to the bishops and their clergie to aunsvver a little booke that came forthe the last parliament, and to other brethren to iudge of it by Gods worde, untill they see it aunsweared, and not to be caryed away with any repect of man.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>An admonition to the parliament.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:12168:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12168:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>¶AN Exhortation to the</hi> By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to deale Brotherly with theyr Brethren.</head>
            <p>ALthough both through lacke of learning and experience / I be farre ſhort in abilitie / to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort or dehort in any reſpect / eſpecially ſythe the matter dothe concerne thoſe that are or ſhoulde be bothe wel learned and experienced themſelues / and thereby vnderſtand more then I can aduiſe: yet being greeued in conſcience / and ſomewhat I finde in you blame worthy / and ſeeing you bende not your knowledge to amende that in you is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe: pardon me though I preſume to admoniſh you in brotherly ſort / as my ſlender ſkill will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. But iuſtly it may be obiected to me that ther are many farre more fitte and able / then I to deale in ſuche a matter / and ſyth they do not / it may be thought great arrogancie in me to intermeddle in the ſame: In deede my want of abilitie / as before / ſo againe I confeſſe / and the great plentie of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that are farre more able / I muſte nedes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge / and withall my heart I wiſhe better willes in men added to their ſkill / then (the Lorde knoweth) are to be found amongſt vs: as for arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie to be imputed to me in this caſe / ſurely I hope there ſhall not / for / God is my witneſſe / I only ſeeke to diſcharge my conſcience in ſhewing my diſlike of that / wherin as I thinke you deale ſcarſe brotherly. If any good fall out hereby I
<pb facs="tcp:12168:2"/> ſhall be glad / and praiſe God for the ſame / if none / yet haue I ſatiſfied mine owne conſcience in vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering my minde. Thus much for excuſe / nowe to the matter. I vnderſtand / beloued in Chriſt / of a certaine booke lately publiſhed abrode by ſome of our brethren / the matter whereof as it is muche miſliked / ſo is the maner not well alowed of / and bothe ſo euill taken as oure poore brethren for the ſame feele the paine and puniſhment of moſt hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous offenders: if theyr fault be great yet they are our brethren / and therfore by you ought ſomwhat to be regarded / if it be not great / as they are oure brethren / you not regarding them / are greatlye to be blamed. And ſurely for my part I thinke your duety were to diſcouer vnto the world by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the worde / howe truely or falſly they haue wrytten / which if you woulde doe in ſymplicitie of conſcience / then perhaps theyr fault would not be ſo greeuous as you make it / wherin I durſte ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale vnto your owne conſcience if the matter did not touch you ſo nearly as it doth. For I pray you examine theyr caſe with me a little: they put forth a Booke in the time of Parliament / wherin they diſcloſe the diſorders of our church of Englande / and humbly deſire a Reformation of the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of Gods worde: is this an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouation? they ſay there oughte to be no Lordli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the miniſterie: Biſhops liuings ought to be abated: theyr great circuites cutte ſhorter: and them ſelues made equall to theyr brethren: is this to ouerthrowe a whole ſtate? they ſay the Booke of common Prayer is full of corruptions / they miſlike with our vnlearned miniſterie / they fynde fault with our diſorderous Diſcipline / and putte downe theyr opinions howe theſe things may be reformed: is this intollerable? theyr Boke ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on many pointes needeleſſe heere to be reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed / and if in any parte therof they ſhew ſuche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous diſobedience towardes our ſoueraigne
<pb facs="tcp:12168:2"/> as ſome ſeeke to enforce / none ſhall thynke them more worthy puniſhment then I: but to ſeeke reformation of deformities in Gods church / to ſay the Biſhops ſhuld be vnlorded and abridged of theyr huge liuings / and to craue that all deformities may be cut of and corrected by the preſcripte rule of Gods holy woorde / is to ſeeke the furtherance of Gods honor and glory / and therfore great blame worthy are they that ſo ſeeke to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate the matter / in charging them with diſobedience to hir Maieſtie / as thoughe to honor the almightie / were to diſhonor the Prince. I maruell that menne of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning profeſſing chriſtian religion / wil contrary to theyr profeſſion deale ſo vnchriſtianlye with theyr brethren: ſurely in my iudgemnt theſe be very ſlender arguments to ſay / theſe men deſyre a reformation / therefore they ſeeke innouations / as thoughe it were ſo ſtraunge a matter to haue a churche reformed / it is as weake an argument to ſay they woulde haue Biſhops vnlorded / theyr liuings abated / the miniſterie broughte to hys right courſe / and true diſcipline reſtored / therefore they would ouerthrow the whole ſtate. A third reaſon is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed / as fond and feeble as the reſt: and that is / that their dealing is vntollerable / ſurely what it is to innouate in your ſenſe I know not / but ſure I am / there can be no innouation found in that motion that hath any parte of Gods woorde to warrant it. For that is farre more auncient then the diſorders of our church / or any order deuiſed by man / and till oure diſorders be remoued and Chriſt his auncient orders ſet in place / till we ceaſe to be guided and ruled by men / and yeelde to be directed by the word of God / I can not hope of any great good in our congregations. As for ouerthrowe of the whole ſtate truely Englande were in a ſtraunge caſe / if the ſtate therof / either in encreaſe or decay / dependeth vpon the maintenance or ouerthrowe of the Biſhops Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and liuings. And as for your argument of intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerableneſſe / in deede in one ſenſe it may holde true / and that is in that your ſelues will not tollerate theyr dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings herein / but aggrauate theyr cauſe to make it ſeme
<pb facs="tcp:12168:3"/> more greuous in the ſight of men / otherwiſe I ſee no reaſon how (iuſtly) theyr doing may be thought intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable / for it maye be counted tollerable that Goddes word doth allowe. But whether theyr booke agree or diſagree with the word of god / I meane not to deale / leauing that to be iudged by the learned / as for me / ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my greefe conceiued / I minde to exhort you to Biſhoply &amp; brotherly dealing with theſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe you beare the titles and names of Lorde and Lordes grace) felowe paſtors and preachers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal word of God / together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you. In dede my purpoſe tended ſomewhat further / but that is cut off by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary report that I haue heard / &amp; therfore leauing this as a thing needeleſſe to be rehearſed I proceede to the matter in hand: Your brethren are in priſon and haue bene theſe many dayes for the booke before named / and which of you all ſince theyr empriſoning hath opened his mouth to ſpeake one word for their deliuerie? nay / which of you hath not inueighed bitterly againſt them by worde / ſince the publiſhing of that booke? They haue bene delt as cloſe priſoners a long time / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no frende / no not ſkarce their wiues may come to them / and which of you all haue ſued for their further liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? nay which of you all hath not bene ready to hinder their libertie ſought for by others? They haue lien lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at great charge / and are very pore and needy / &amp; which of you all hath opened your purſſe to releeue them? if any of you haue (though it be your dueties) I muſte needees commend him or them: if none of you / as it is your dueties / I muſt nedes condemne you. A lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table caſe that Lording ſhould ſo lead away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heartes of the learned / that they forget their dueties in theyr calling: for ſee how fouly you forget your ſelues: Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes lie abrode in your dioceſſes vntouched / in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the truth and her Maieſties lawes / refuſe to frequent diuine ſeruice and ſermons / and yet if anye honeſt man preſent them vnto you / a fauorable ſpeeche or letter of ſome worſhipfull (though not very godly) in the Shire / ſhall eaſely obtaine their diſpatche. But
<pb facs="tcp:12168:3"/> if any of our brethren ſtriue or endeuoure them ſelues zealouſly to further the building of Gods temple / and to procure reformation of things amiſſe / it is eaſelye ſeene by theſe / what helpe they ſhoulde haue at youre handes / and if a chriſtian brother make ſute for hym / fauoure is hardly obtained / or not at all / if it fall oute otherwiſe / by this I ſhall be glad and yeelde my ſelfe faultie in ſaying thus of you. Many leud light bokes and ballades flie abrode printed / not only wythout re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion / but cum priuilegio / the authors and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters wherof continue daily amongſt vs without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolment / and yet the Lord by his holy ſcriptures for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth all filthy communication / &amp; therfore wryting: but if any of our brethren put in Print any booke of a godly zeale / that tendeth to the furtherance of Goddes glory and ſinceritie / and vrgeth a reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of things amiſſe / he is newe fangled / he is not frende to Ceſar / he is to be remoued from amongſt the people. Alaſſe deare brethren what hathe ſo bewitched and blineded you / that you can not perceiue / and ſee your owne euil dealing heerein? if the title of Lordſhip / caſt it off / if your huge liuings / forſake them: be not ſo wrapped in the deſire of worldly things / that you neglecte youre dueties in your vocation and calling: I can not think ſo well of you / but that I muſt needes ſay you neglect your dueties: I thincke ſurely there is none of you but would be gladde to ſee reformation of things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe / for ſome of you I knowe haue ſayde ſo / neither can you deny but that many things are out of order in our Church of England / euen many things that they make mention of in their boke: what then moueth you to make their offence ſo greeuous in the ſighte of the worlde / or rather why doe you not allowe that is good in their booke / ſeeing they ſeeke reformation therby of that you would gladly ſee reformed your ſelues: ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I thinke (to ſpeake my conſcience) that there are ſome things in the boke / which gladly you wold haue omitted / that hindereth your liking of the reſt / &amp; that is the inueying againſt your Lordſhips and liuings / 
<pb facs="tcp:12168:4"/> for moſt of you would be glad to haue all remnauntes of Poperie / ſuperſtition / and Idolatrye vtterly remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / but none of you would willingly loſe his Lordly dignitie and liuing / <hi>Hinc illae lachrymae</hi> againſt your pore brethren / hence riſeth your diſlike / this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe you ſeke not their deliuerance / libertie and releaſe / you would be glad of a reformation / but you would not be reformed your ſelues / but in theſe things / there is but one truth or falſhode. If they holde the truth / why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſiſte you it in theſe priuate reſpectes to pleaſe youre ſelues? if their opinion be falſe / ſhewe the reaſon and then will we beleeue you / but wreſt not the worde to ſatiſfie your owne fanſie / and whether your honoures and Lordſhips ſtand or fall / let not the holy ſcriptures loſe their due dignitie and reuerence. It is a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thing to beholde howe (to make theyr owne mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters good) men wil in theſe dayes mangle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures of God / but the Lorde will not be ſo dallied with all / howe ſo euer they pleaſe to dally with the ſimple men of the world / and he wil be reuenged on you for negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting to ſee this foule fault redreſſed. But to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe oure brethren lie in priſon / where beſides their bondes they lacke libertie of enioyinge the company of their frendes / and haue great neede to be releeued: let them in ſome ſorte finde you carefull and mindefull of them / trauaile for their deliuerie / if that wil not be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained / yet endeuoure to procure them ſome further li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie / if neither will be had / forget not to releue them. Their boke is out and cannot be called backe againe / if it may be iuſtified by the word of truth / take heede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by you the truthe be not betraied / trie it by the touche ſtone / examine it by the word / ſet al affections aparte / thinke it no diſgrace to come downe from your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dignities / if the worde of the Lorde will haue it ſo. Feede not your owne fantaſies / but follow the word / &amp; thinke not ſcorne to be controlled by the ſame word / out of whoſe mouth ſo euer it come. Balaam was a Prophet of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord / yet at one inſtant his Aſſe taught him a better leſſon than he could teach him ſelfe / I am
<pb facs="tcp:12168:4"/> not to teache you / neither meane I ſo to take vppon me / only I exhort you to deale Biſhoply and brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / and let no vaine loue of Lorldly dignitie make you careleſſe of your brethren / who wiſhe you good in the Lord / though they would be glad you were vnlorded / not for malice / but becauſe ſcripture alloweth no ſuche title to a Biſhop. If paſſionate affection ſhall ſo cary you away / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> becauſe your Lordlineſſe is touched / you will therefore not deale ſo / but againſt your brethren I knowe not what others wil conceiue therof / but for my part (to ſpeake as I thinke) I muſt nedes doubt / your Lordlineſſe hath made you vtterly to forget what ought to be in a Biſhop. If they do holde any error or behaue themſelues licenciouſly and loſely / or neglected their vocation / I were eaſily put to ſilence / but in doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine they are ſounde / in life not to be touched / that euer I heard / and were diligent in their calling: why then ſhould you ſo little eſteeme them / or why ſhoulde you not vſe them as brethren / let it not be truly ſaid of you / that the blaſphemous ſwearer / and the filthy adulterer may finde more fauoure among you then our chriſtian brethren / and fellowe workemen in the Lord / I know for the firſt of theſe there is no lawe to touche him / and for the ſeconde very ſlender puniſhment prouided / yet for both the Lord hath left vnto vs very ſharp lawes / theſe are vnexecuted / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked eſcape many times for mony. Many good lawes (thankes be to God) are prouided to bridle the wicked / but in them oftentimes the godly are ſnared / and by them you youre ſelues (if not nowe) yet at other times haue bene inſtruments to burthen your brethrens backes / and that hath ſome of them felt in more ſharpe ſorte (as I haue heard) then I will hear ſpeake. Well / let that paſſe / and now deale more chriſtianly for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes ſake with your brethren / let not lawes that were purpoſely made for the wicked / be made ſnares by you to catch the godly / lay aſide this Lording / and ſhew your ſelues brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in deede / if they haue offended you / admoniſh them brotherly / let not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſurped names and titles of Lorde &amp; Lordes grace ſo
<pb facs="tcp:12168:5"/> puffe you vp / as you forget your ſelues to be paſtors, preachers: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord called you or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt of you to this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to ioyne as laborers togither w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his vineyarde / he neuer called you to theſe lordly names &amp; dignities: the office of biſhop I finde apointed by ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: the office of Lordbiſhop I finde no warrant for there / but in this I mean not to wade further / only I beſeche you / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as Chriſt hath allotted you to be fellow miniſters togither w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them / ſo you wil as companions in the Lord ioyne togither to further one truth &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie / &amp; let theſe pore men taſt of your chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charity towards them / as brethren / and ceaſe lordly to neglect them / &amp; Lord it no longer / think it no diſcredit to you / or an abaſing of your ſelues / to ioyn in equaliti w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your brethren / but think it great preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption in you to clime higher then the lord hath appointed: remember it was not in vain ſaid of Chriſt our ſauiour / <hi>Principes gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dominantur in eas, &amp;c: inter vos autem non erat ſic,</hi> I ſeeke not to teach / neither take I vpon me ſo to do / yet deſpiſe not the admonition of your faithful brother in the Lord / who wiſheth to you all ſuch god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſideration of your dueties / as in no reſpecte you omit any parte thereof.</p>
            <p>To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude / in the name of god I beſeche you yeld no ſuch frutes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel / as where you ſhuld be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful / you ſhew your ſelues careleſſe of your brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter ouer in ſuch ſort as you haue done / from one to an other / but ſo longe as they keepe them within the limites of the law of god: ioyne chriſtianly &amp; brotherly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them &amp; aſſiſt them / and ceaſe ſo to affect lordſhip &amp; liuing as therby you be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>drawne from yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a knowne &amp; manifeſt truth. The Lord in his rich mercy giue euery of vs grace ſo to auoid all ſnares of ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as wholy w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out let or hinderance we may be dedicated vnto him / and yeeld our ſelues all together obedient vnto his wil / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what he hathe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded we may ſtriue to maintain / &amp; what he hath forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / we may indeuor to ſuppreſſe. Thus praying your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable acceptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereof I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit you to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord Ieſus.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:12168:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>An Exhortation to THE BISHOPS AND THEIR CLER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie to aunſvver a little booke that came forthe the</hi> laſt Parliament / and to other Brethren to iudge of it by Gods worde / vntill they ſee it aunſweared / and not to be caryed away with any reſpect of man.</head>
            <p>COnſidering the vnitie of the body of Chriſte which are we (bicauſe it is gouerned wyth one heade and one ſpirite / and yet notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding a diuerſitie of parts and membres / for the bodye is not one member / for if they were all one member / where were the bodye)?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.13.14.19.</note> I haue to directe my talke to a whole bodye / yet ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eyther parte hearken to that only which is belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vnto him / not ſnatching y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnto him / whiche is not proper to him / and vnto euery member ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally / but in ſuche ſort / that they be not deuided or cutte a parte from the whole. There are in the Churche of Chriſte eyes and eares / there are alſo handes and feete / to eyther of theſe I haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to make / for theyr profite / if they heare it / to their ſmart / if they reiecte it.<note place="margin">15.26.</note> I ſpeake vnto them in the Lords name / and do herein but his meſſage. I require vnderſtanding eares therfore / &amp; watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eyes / I demaund diligent hands / and painfull feete. It is not vnknowne (brethren) howe it hath pleaſed the Lorde of late to bring forthe to the eyes and hands of you all a little ſcroll / conteining as you know / matters concerning the true refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and building of gods church / whether it tend in deede to that ende or noe / I haue not here to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate
<pb facs="tcp:12168:6"/>
/ but that it pretendeth / at this I haue ſeene ſome ſtormyng / as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greif of man is eaſily to be perceaued: and the authors of it / as we know alſo / are in the place of theeues &amp; murtherers: for them I haue noughte els to ſay / but that they are there iuſtly / if falſely and vntruly they haue gone about to ſpoyle and robbe vs of an vnfayned truthe / and murther oure ſoules wyth a corrupt and poyſoned water / drawn out of a ſtinking puddel of the filthy dunghill of mannes braynes. For how were that to be ſuffered in the ciuil lawes of earthly princes / that ſome one of the commen ſorte / or els other / ſhould go about to diſanul the order &amp; law ſet out by the Prynce / Gods lieuetenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in earth in thoſe caſes / to place his owne deuiſe? muche more in the houſe of God / which is his churche. To me it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a thing ſo vntollerable / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the New gates and olde gates yea and all tibournes in Englande are too little for ſuch raſh and preſumtious heads / that will not geue God leaue to rule / but will take the ſcepter out of his hande. Being more ouer and beſides that / a ſhamefull &amp; horrible thing to make ſtrife and contention betweene the people of God / which are commaunded to be one as theyr heade / and his father are one.<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.22</note> It was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte and neweſt commaundement that Chriſte lefte vnto vs / that we ſhould loue one a nother / euen as he loued vs / and thys he tolde vs / ſhould be a ſigne wherby we ſhould be knowen to be his diſciples / if we loue one an other as he loued vs / which is not fleſhlye or carnally / or for any worldly reſpecte / but in the conſent and agreement of his commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement / in folowing the preſcrypt of his worde / wherin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the cauſe of all our loue / and cauſe of al ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred / euen of our parents / when they ſwarue from it:<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.11 13.35.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 14.23.15.10.14. mat. 10.35</note> whych ſurely cannot be maintained / where new and ſtraunge orders in Gods matters are inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / broched / and publyſhed / be who ſo be may / the cauſers or founders of ſuche deuiſes. And
<pb facs="tcp:12168:6"/> therefore better it were for them / that a mylſtone were hanged about theyr neckes / &amp; they drouned in the myddeſt of the ſea / then one of the leaſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of Chriſte / ſhould be offended by theyr deuiſes.<note place="margin">mat. 18.0.</note> But as I ſayd / I mind not to entreate of that matter / my deſire is / &amp; that for Iſraels ſake / I meane the children and churche of God / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which are the eyes of the churche / &amp; are oure ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers to watche for our ſoules (for oure bloud muſt be required at theyr hands) wolde take this matter in hand / to debate the equitie &amp; truth of the cauſe / by the ſcriptures and worde of God / which is the only foode of oure ſoules / and ſtay for the direction of all oure godly actions / that we the ſheepe of Chriſt might knowe falſe fodder from true / corne from chaffe / Schiſme from Truthe / Chriſt from Antichriſte.<note place="margin">Eze. 3.17.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.27 Heb. 5.12. Pſal. 119.105.</note> The accuſation is gréeuous where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our cleargy is burdened / they are indired as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> folowers of Antichriſt / their myniſterie is vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to be from the Pope / theyr ſuperioritie which they haue by order of thys realme / as Lords ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall / and a neceſſary part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high houſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament in eſtabliſhyng politique lawes for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the common weale / beſyde the iuriſdiction epiſcopal / which they haue ouer theyr dioceſſes / is there condemned as a thing in no wiſe tollerable by the word of God / which thing amaſeth &amp; daſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the eyes of vs the ſimpler and vnlearned ſort / that we knowe not howe to eſteeme of them / or of our ſelues / if the truthe be ſo / we ought not to hear them / although they ſpeake a truth / more then the deuill was to be ſuffered / althoughe he profeſſed Chriſt.<note place="margin">Luk. 4.41</note> If it be not ſo / we maruell why ſo ſhort &amp; piuyſhe a thyng is not by them aunſwered / that many ſimple-men / which will well to gods cauſe / and are ſomwhat ſhaken with this pamflet / might haue better ſtay / that they be not caried away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it. Therfore my humble ſute is to the learnedder parte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Chriſte / and the behalfe of his
<pb facs="tcp:12168:7"/> congregation / that they would aunſwer it &amp; healpe vs which are vnlearned. And heere in I ſhall in Gods name / and as they will aunſwere at the laſt day / exhort them to vſe ſymple &amp; ſyncere dealing / and not to wring the ſcripture to ſerue their owne turne / or other mennes phantaſies. For if they do / it wyl eaſely be ſpied: and beſide other inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that will inſue therof / the people whome they ſhall deceiue thereby / ſhall be their condemnation at that day. Cogge not therfore / nor forſte / neither bumbaſte it with Rhetoricke / or mans authoritiy to make a ſhew / but let the word of the eternall be iudge betweene bothe / which is goulde and ſiluer / and which is droſſe and ſtubble: which is corne / and which is chaffe. Call I beſeeche you / to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance this ſaying of an a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient father. <hi>quam ſapiens argumentatrix ſibi videtur humana igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertullian lib. de ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taculis.</note> 
               <hi>praeſertim cum aliquid de gaudijs et fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſeculi metuit amittere?</hi> Howe wyſe a dyſputer (ſayth Tertullian) doth mannes ignorance ſeeme to it ſelfe / chiefely when it feareth to loſe any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or worldly profyt. But anſwere I pray you the whole booke / and not by peeces / for otherwyſe your doings wyll be ſuſpected / neyther doe it in hudder mudder / or ſecretely / or in a tonge that the people knowe not / for then it wyll be ſayde that you dare not publyſhe it / but doe it openly / that all the people may ſee that you ſtand vpon a good grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / vpon whych if you doe ſtand / let not your doyngs feare the lyghte.<note place="margin">Iob. 10.12</note> Wee craue nothing of them / but what they are bounde vnto of duerye / they are our wachmen: wee take / yea rather they themſelues take theſe for wolues / why then do they not chaſe them away? They are faſt inough ye will ſay. It is true / but theyr tales are not? they free as fire brands from place to place / and ſet all the country on fyre. It is requiſyte alſo that they be pryſoned; but that wil not otherwiſe be / they w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lyke rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt captiuate reaſon / a word wil not be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:12168:7"/> but with a woorde / the keyes of the kingdome of heauen muſt come forthe heere / or els the keyes of Newgate will doe no good. And if they doe not come torche / ignorant men and ſymple / wyll ſaye that the other are to lyttle purpoſe brought forthe. There is a better way for Biſſops / and Biſhops of Chriſt / to confute a ſchiſme by / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſons and chaynes: thoſe were and are Antichriſtes biſhops arguments being taken a parte: as they are the iuſt weapons of a lawfull and godly Maieſtrate / if the other goe before. Some ſay they reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber wel that godly ſaying of that lerned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Auguſtin / I think it bee: <hi>Si terrerentur et non docerentur improba quaſi dominatio videretur.</hi> If they ſhuld be feared &amp; not taught / it myght ſeme a wicked gouernance / the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t not practiſed of the cleargy / they are glad to ſee theyr Prince to come wyth <hi>terrerentur,</hi> they would as fame ſee the Biſhops come with <hi>doce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur.</hi> So you ſee what of duetie they require / and ſurely let me ſay wyth your Honors patience what I thinke / is it not a great diſcredyte to your Lordſhips that ſuch a ſcalde trifeling boke can not be anſwered in thys ſeaſon? It is very ſhorte / you beare vs in hande it is folyſhe / ioyne the follye of it wyth the breuitye / it myght eaſely haue beene aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered ere thys; If there had beene taken almoſte but for euery leafe a moneth: there are ſkarce ſo many leaues in it / as there are monthes paſt ſynce it came forthe / what remayneth then / but that I renue my ſute / that herein (wyth the conſyderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chryſt and hys flocke) you woulde haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to your owne honoures and creadyte / that it be not further ſpred / and ſayd you could not anſwer it? They doe not ſatiſfye them ſelues wyth polly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyque reaſons / in that that ſome ſay euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your L. that it is a ſubuerſyon of a ſtate / it is a greate troublyng of a gouernaunce. They ſay the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not / whether it be troubleſome to bryng that in whych they woulde / but whether it be a truthe
<pb facs="tcp:12168:8"/> that thoſe men ſay or no? If that be once reſolued / then haue they to ſtay them ſelues: They are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye enough to obiect the difficulty of Elyas tyme / howe hard a thyng it was in the eares of the kyng &amp; people to ſpeake to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhip of one god / which were nowe dotyng worſhyppers of theyr Balims:<note place="margin">1. re. 18.17.</note> what an impoſſible thing it was to bring in the true prieſthode of Moſes amongſt a ſorte of Idolaters whych hadde caſte Moſes oute of the temple.<note place="margin">mat. 21.33. Ioh. 19.12 Acts. 4.7.</note> They haue the example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles at the fyngers ende / and that the prieſtes then ſayde / by what authority doſt thou this. And agayne to Pilate / if thou let hym go thou arte not Ceſar hys frende. In hys good and iuſte purpoſe they could accuſe hym of treaſon / of a conſpiracye / and for theyr owne partes aſke hym by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority / and ſo is it nowe ſay they wyth oure By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops / they goe not to the ſcryptures as Chryſte wylleth in the perſon of the ſcrybes / but they crye out agaynſt theſe pore men they are not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quenes freendes / they make a trouble in a ſtate / theſe and ſuche lyke are theyr wordes / your honoures haue to conſyder vpon the mater accordyngly. And thus muche to your honoures wyſhyng youre ſauetye / if it ſo pleaſe God wythout any ſhakyng / and that your thrones may ſtande for euer / if they be from God / whych theſe men ſeeme to call in doute / and I truſt your Lordſhips wil ſhew in vaine / &amp; how vaynely they ſtande. Nowe to you my brethren / whych are of the inferioure ſort / I haue to deſyre you to cleaue to the truthe / and be not moued for what ſo euer. If thys be truth whych our honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable cleargy doe nowe maintayne / caſt away that peeuyſhe and fonde booke / let not a leafe of paper ſcrabled / and blyndly by ſtealthe Prynted / more preuayle wyth you / then an order ſo long mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned by auncyent canons and ciuill lawe / let not one or two priuate men of no accompt or counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance / more perſuade wyth you then multytudes
<pb facs="tcp:12168:8"/> of good place / and doers in the behalfe of your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Prynce and Countrey. Let not the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of yong menne preuaile agaynſte the graye heades of olde fathers: for ſo may you quickly fall from a truthe / and goe aſtray when you thyncke you goe ſtrayghte.<note place="margin">1. reg. 12.8</note> Set before you the example of Rehoboam / who if he had folowed the aduyſe of hys olde counſellers / and not the raſhe and greene heades of yong men / hys kyngdome had not bene ſo ſoone rent from hym.<note place="margin">1. reg. 1.21. Act. 4.19.5.30.</note> But if on the contrary ſyde / the truthe goe on theyr ſyde / if by good and dilygent conference of the ſcryptures / you maye ſee that they are in the ryght way / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what other counſell ſhould I gyue you / but if Baall be God / folowe hym: if the Lord be God / follow hym / bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is to obay God than ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Better it is to goe ſtrayghte wyth Elias and Chriſt / then to goe a whoryng wyth all the Baalites / Scribes / and Phariſies: a multitude may as eaſly erre as one / it was ſo then / it is ſo nowe / foure hundreth and fiftie Prophets of Baal for one Elias / foure hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred falſe Prophets agaynſte one Micheas:<note place="margin">1. re. 18.22. 1. reg. 22.6</note> the moſt part of the world nowe Mahometiſtes and Papiſtes: and ſurely it was truely ſayd of hym / who ſo euer he were <hi>Nihil omnino agimus qui nos per multitudinis exempla defendimus.</hi> We doe nothing at al / which defend our ſelues by example of the multytude: Not alwayes the beſt learned were the wiſeſt in Gods matters: example of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus / who vnderſtode not what it was to be born agayn:<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.4. Ioh. 9.30. mar. 7.2.3.</note> Not alwayes the wyſeſt fauor wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome moſte / but rather reſyſt it / and ſtriue more for the waſhyng of hands and pottes then they do for the kyngdome of God. Maſters of religyon are not alwayes the moſt zealous in ſettyng forth a truthe / ſometymes they can ſay to the pore lame man / <hi>Sabbathum eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.10.</note> it is the ſabboth day / <hi>non li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet tibi tollere grabbatum:</hi> it is not lawful for thee to take vp thy bedde: and if the blynde wyll ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:12168:9"/> and diſpute wyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and ſay that Chriſte is not <hi>homo peccator</hi> a ſynfull man / althoughe to theyr thinkyng / <hi>Sabbathum non ſeruat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 9.34.</note> he keepeth not the Sabbothe / he ſhall be excommunicate. The vnlearned ſometyme are ſo allowed of God for theyr good and godly endeuors / that he maketh them ſcholemayſters of the learned and great doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Looke vppon pore Philip howe he inſtructed Nathanaell <hi>Inuenim sillum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.46.</note> we haue founde him of whome Moſes wrote / and the Prophets euen Ieſus the ſonne of Ioſephe / that man of Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. And lette not the vileneſſe of Nazareth anye thyng amaſe vs / ſuch falſe preiudicies may ſhutte vp the kyngdome of heauen agaynſte vs / we can not ſay that no good can come oute of pore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſtudyes / if we do ſo / we ſhoulde ſpeake folyſhly as they did in thoſe dayes / can there any goodneſſe come from Nazareth. God is not in deede bounde to Nazareth:<note place="margin">Mark. 1. Luk. 2.8. Math. 22. Mat. 28 Ioh. 20.18</note> no more is he debarred from doing good by Nazareth: he is not bounde to any poore ſimple man: no more is he cut of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhewing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Angels vnto ſhepherds / &amp; hymſelf to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men / but ſlender meſſengers to the ſyghte of the worlde / to enforme the worlde and wittie of the byrth and reſurrection of Chryſt. It ſaythe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentymes alſo / that the wyſe and myghtye men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world wil ſay to Chriſt / of &amp; agaynſt the crying out of his pore diſciples) chyde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">Lu. 19.39.</note> But if they do you know what Chriſt ſayd at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme / &amp; he ſayth ſo now to: I tell you / if theſe hold theyr peaces / the ſtones ſhall ſtraight way cry out: his diſciples may holde theyr peace / I ſay the Biſhops maye hold theyr peace / and I ſay becauſe Chriſt ſayde / ſtones / theſe ſtones may ſpeake: There may be a foule gloſe made vpon a good matter / an euyll fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured cloke put vppon a faire body: The truthe may be accuſed of ſedition / of trouble / of breaking of ſtates / <note place="margin">Act. 14.5.</note> if it be ſo / it is no newe thyng / if ye bee once aſſured of an vndouted truthe / if it be not
<pb facs="tcp:12168:9"/> foule wythin / &amp; faire wythout / if it be gold &amp; ſyluer / and not ſtubble grounded vpon the true foundation Ieſus Chriſt care you not / for that Chriſt called his truth a ſword / a fyre / and he himſelfe long agoe was ſpyted at for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / &amp; accuſed to.<note place="margin">Luk. 20 20. Iohn. 11 20. Mat. 10 25.</note> 
               <hi>Non eſt ſeruus ſupra ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrum,</hi> there is no ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aboue his maſter / if they called the maſter of the houſe Belzebub / how much more them of his houſhold? the more y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men are cried out vpon for callyng for the practiſe of Gods word / if it ſhuld deſtroy al policies in the world / (although they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſay ſo / ſay nothing / for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary is true / the practiſyng of Gods word / &amp; walking in hys religion vprightly / is the eſtabliſhing and ſtrengthenyng of kyngdoms) the more I ſay they are cried out vpon / the more they ought to goe forwards / as wel as the blynde man dyd / when whole multytudes bad hym hold hys peace: they may not ceaſe I ſay / althoughe whole multytudes cry out agaynſt them / &amp; ſay hold your peace / holde your peace / if they will be reſtored to theyr ſyght / &amp; be delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blindeneſſe to cry / &amp; to cry out a loud:<note place="margin">Luk. 15.39.</note> Thou ſonne of Dauid haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy on me: Theſe pore men may cry out / yea ought to cry out / if they ſee vs in blindneſſe / O ſonne of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid haue mercy on them / and ſo they deſerue our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure &amp; frendſhip / rather then pryſons &amp; Newgate: if we be blinde / I ſay if we be / for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil be diſcuſſed I truſt by the learned. And if they hold theyr peace / we haue to thynke we are in blyndneſſe / &amp; that they cry wel / ſonne of Dauid haue mercye vppon vs. In dede if theyr boke be true (and that I may ſpeake as one of you / ſimple &amp; vnlearned / I ſhall thinke it to be true / vntil I ſee it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed by the ſcriptures) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil I alſo as wel as you / as well as they / cry out in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyte of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude / becauſe I haue a greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre to be reſtored to ſyght / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feare to dyſpleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / O ſonne of Dauid haue mercy vppon vs: And if all Ieruſalem ſhuld be diſpleaſed becauſe I ſay / bleſſed is he that commeth in the name of the lord / yet wold I alone cry out / bleſſed is he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commeth in the name
<pb facs="tcp:12168:10"/> of the Lord / were it as new and as ſtrange as it was then / ſeeme it neuer ſo great a monſter to cal the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritanes from worſhipping in the mountaine Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razim / or the Iewes from the ſetled place Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem / from an olde and auncient cuſtome / which hath poſſeſſyon many hundreth yeres / yet had I rather be with Chriſte / than wyth the woman of Samarie / vntil ſhe come to Chriſt.<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.20.</note> Antiquitie may deceiue vs, nay we ſee it hathe deceiued vs / I can not tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it wold ſtil deceiue: it is not true to ſay / it is old / therfore it is good:<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.30.</note> Sathan hath bene Lord of thys world a great while: Antichriſt of Rome pleadeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> continuance of many yeres (I know not) how many C. yeres / neyther doth it follow it is new / therfore it was nought:<note place="margin">Mar. 1.27.</note> it was ſayd to Chriſt / what new doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is thys: yet it was no falſe doctrine: ſo ſayd the falſe prieſtes &amp; Biſhops of Paules doctrine and the reſt / but it was not therefore naught:<note place="margin">Act. 24.14.</note> wil you trie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old and the newe / and ſee in deede which is the new / which is the olde / ſearch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures. If it be found there / it is olde / ſay Biſhops what they will / let the Prieſtes call it as new as they liſt: if it be not found there / it is newe / let them ſay what they can / &amp; bring neuer ſo many fathers / and neuer ſo good fathers: better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe brought / I am ſure they can not / and yet dyd Chriſt preuaile / and ſo will he ſtill: for he is the ſame in his worde / that he was then in bodely preſence / the wryting of the Apoſtles doe paint him out truely / and nothing but him. If it be true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſay / that this aucthoritie of Biſhops / &amp; churche hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie which they maintain / come from the Pope / and hath no ground but in his law / and that God can not ſuffer to be ſerued according to mens pleaſures in ruling of his houſe / as though he wer ſuch a fole y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he could not ſet order himſelf or wer careleſſe (which is no point of wyt) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did not: or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſee ſo little / as to deuiſe an order which could not be for al times &amp; places / ſo that we ſhould haue nede of a new holy ghoſt / (for al this foloweth vpon that ground y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſtand vpon) away wyth that vile doctrine / or what
<pb facs="tcp:12168:10"/> ſo euer ye liſt to terme it / what inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience ſo euer wer like to enſue / what antiquitie ſo euer be againſt it / for you ſee there is a blaſphemie ioyned with it / which maketh our God a foliſh / a careleſſe / an vncir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumſpect / and vnprouident god. Wel / peraduenture they ſee ſomthing more then they ſay / &amp; ſome things I am ſure they would haue to be reformed / which they can not bring to paſſe as they would / &amp; therfore thinke it better with pollicie to ſaue the goſpell / then to haue it cleane ſhut out: It is a common ſaying of two euils it is beſt to chuſe the leaſt:<note place="margin">Ih. 10.1</note> better it is to haue a goſpel of Chriſt ioyned with a peece of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte / then to haue none at all: thus they perſuade them ſelues / the other doe not ſo / they thincke it not lawful to ioyne God &amp; Belial together: ſurely they haue ſome reaſon / nay they haue greate reaſon / for what ſocietie hathe light wyth darkneſſe.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6 14.</note> If all the world myght be gained w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a little breache of Gods word / it were not to be done / better it were that the whole world ſhould peariſhe / then one iote of Gods truth ſhould be ouer ſlipped:<note place="margin">Ih. 19.1.</note> Pilate thought he had behaued himſelfe wiſely when he whipped Chriſte / and put vpon hym a robe of ſcarlet / thinking by that meanes / making him to appeare vile to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes / to haue had him let goe / that they might haue conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with that litle puniſhment / &amp; ſo might Chriſt haue preached ſtill. But it is wickedly done to policie the matters of Chriſt after that ſort. Who ſo euer thinketh by putting a foles cote vpon Chriſt and clothing him with a garment which is not his owne / to entertain him ſtill / &amp; thinketh he is content by ſuch means to haue lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to go preaching amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the people / he deceiueth himſelf / &amp; ſhal right wel vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand at the day of accomptes / that God will not be mocked. Thus in ſome reſpect you haue well to weigh the things that are put forth vnto you / by the ſcriptures / without further circumſtances / leaſte in leauing the rule / ye go out of rule. But I doute not but our lords &amp; clergy wil quickly ſhew you whether
<pb facs="tcp:12168:11"/> it be wel ruled or no / they haue ſaid already in theyr ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to you / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is a very foliſh boke / I truſt they wil giue it vnto you in wryting / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better way both. But before al things take hede to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word let not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhew of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deceiue you: Peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſome of you wil be perſuaded / bicauſe a biſhop an olde ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / a very learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith ſo / bicauſe this ſtate hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a great while many yeares amongſt good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.39. Act. 1.21</note> do not ſo / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is no warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word / you haue had exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples inough to ſhew vnto you / how eaſie it is to be deceiued therin / on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide let not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of men beare you away / for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> way alſo you may erre: the only ſtraight way (as I haue tolde you) to kepe you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> going aſtray / is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god / wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they as wel as you / I truſt / will be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be tried / otherwiſe they haue no grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d againſt the papiſtes: if they wil not / but refuſe to be iudged by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word / leue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there / thoſe pore priſoners haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right / whether they be whipped &amp; ſcurged / or vtterly ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged / &amp; aſſure your ſelues as wel of them as of your ſelues / if they ſuffer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt / they ſhalbe glorified w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt / &amp; ſo ſhall you.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> That we may ſo do / god giue vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth / &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we know it to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtedfaſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the loue of the world / &amp; feare of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not more preuaile w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs then the loue of heauen and feare of god. Theſe things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue ſaide vnto you rudely / I pray you take in good part (good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) both you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lerned ſort / &amp; you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler / I pray you lay forth the truthe / as your duetie bindeth you / &amp; you giue eare to the truthe. Confute ſciſmes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures / &amp; iudge you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſcriptures alſo / as priſons be vſed / ſo let the worde which is the armor of your warfare be practiſed: Let not newe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate be the only meanes to ſtay falſe procedings: If you do ſo / where error is redreſſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate / you ſhalbe iudged becauſe you dyd not your duety / &amp; bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way if they be out / or bi ſuch good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they bring you home. The which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of al mercies graunt through his ſonne Chriſt by our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortor the holy ghoſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12168:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
